Timothy James Leffel

updated dec17/2017

tjleffel@gmail.com
+1(614)306-7814

http://lefft.xyz 🏵 github.com/lefft 🗘

ABOUT

I'm a generative linguist by training, and a research/data scientist by profession. I've worked on projects ranging from document classification and topic modeling to data ingestion and automated reporting. I approach NLP problems with industry standard tooling and the intuitions of an empirically-focused language scientist. Enthusiast of: R, Python, the NBA, the history of math/logic, math/logic.

WORK EXPERIENCE

- 2016– Research Scientist, Academic Research Centers. NORC at the University of Chicago.
 - >> social media text mining (sentiment analysis, document classification, topic modeling)
 - >> pre-processing; training and evaluation; regression; simulation and resampling; visualization
 - >> development of data ingestion pipelines and automated reporting systems for RCTs
- 2015 Data science intern (p/t). Vantage Sports Inc.
 - >> development and implementation of daily fantasy sports lineup optimization algorithm
 - >> evaluation of competing predictive models for daily fantasy performance of NBA players
- 2014–16 Postdoctoral Researcher. Language Processing Lab, Department of Linguistics. University of Chicago
 - >> experimental design and implementation (surveys, eye-tracking for visual world studies)
 - >> data analysis and modeling (mixed-effects and logistic regression, RM-ANOVA, others)
 - >> dissemination of research results (conference presentations, proceedings and journal papers)
- 2010–16 Adjunct Instructor and Teaching Assistant in Linguistics and Psychology.
 - >> primary instructor or TA for various undergrad courses in linguistics and psychology
 - >> 2016 at the University of Chicago; 2010–2014 at New York University

EDUCATION

2014	PhD, Linguistics. New York University
2011	MA, Linguistics. New York University

2009 BA with honors, magna cum laude, Linguistics/Philosophy. The Ohio State University

TECHNICAL SKILLS

programming and scientific computing

- >> **R** core packages: dplyr, ggplot2, purrr, lme4, rstan, quanteda. Happy in base or hadleyverse.
- >> **Python**—core libraries: pandas, numpy, scipy, nltk, spacy, scikit—learn. Usually use i Python/Jupyter.
- >> basic competency in Javascript, Haskell, Julia, Matlab. Quick and enthusiastic learner.

algorithms, analysis techniques, etc.

- >> NLP: multinomial naive Bayes; decision trees; LDA; n-gram probability models; morphological analysis
- >> regression modeling (OLS, logistic, mixed-effects, censored, poisson); NHST; Bayesian estimation

other skills

>> AWS cloud computing (EC2/S3); (R)markdown; Shiny; basic web development; git; github; ETFX